<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Exceeding joyfull nevves from Darby: declaring how Endimion Porter was taken at the grange neere Westhallum within 5. miles of Darby, on the 15. day of Septemb. 1642. Also the taking of Sr. Iohn Watson, neer Hartford, with the true proceedings at Bristow, Bath Warwicke, Boston, Yorke shire, Northumberland, Darby-shire, Cheshire, and Northampton-shire. With a true information of his Majesties removall from Nottingham to Darby. Likewise how the cavaliers made an attempt against Boston, but was opposed by the country, 14. slaine and three taken prisners. Also a true declaration how the Welshmen was driven out of Cheshire, by the forces under the command of the Earle of Essex.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84239</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E118_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19313</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860638</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860638</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156089</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84239)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156089)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 21:E118[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Exceeding joyfull nevves from Darby: declaring how Endimion Porter was taken at the grange neere Westhallum within 5. miles of Darby, on the 15. day of Septemb. 1642. Also the taking of Sr. Iohn Watson, neer Hartford, with the true proceedings at Bristow, Bath Warwicke, Boston, Yorke shire, Northumberland, Darby-shire, Cheshire, and Northampton-shire. With a true information of his Majesties removall from Nottingham to Darby. Likewise how the cavaliers made an attempt against Boston, but was opposed by the country, 14. slaine and three taken prisners. Also a true declaration how the Welshmen was driven out of Cheshire, by the forces under the command of the Earle of Essex.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Fowler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Septem. 20. 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Porter, Endymion, 1587-1649.</term>
               <term>Watson, John, --  Sir.</term>
               <term>Essex, Robert Devereux, --  Earl of, 1591-1646.</term>
               <term>Derbyshire (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156089:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EXCEEDING IOYFVLL NEVVES FROM DARBY: Declaring how <hi>Endimion Porter</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at the <hi>Grange</hi> neere <hi>Weſthallum</hi> within 5. Miles of <hi>Darby,</hi> on the 15. day of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1643.</p>
            <p>Alſo the taking of Sr. <hi>Iohn Watſon,</hi> neer <hi>Hartford,</hi> with the true proceedings at <hi>Briſtow, Bath Warwicke, Boſton, Yorke-ſhire, Northumherland, Darby-ſhire, Cheſhire,</hi> and <hi>Northampton-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a true information of his Majeſties removall from <hi>NOTTINGHAM</hi> to <hi>DARBY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe how the Cavaliers made an attempt againſt <hi>Boſton,</hi> but was oppoſed by the Country, 14. ſlaine and three taken priſners.</p>
            <p>Alſo a true Declaration how the <hi>Welſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> was driven out of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> by the Forces under the command of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for HENRY FOWLER. <hi>Septem.</hi> 20. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:156089:2"/>
            <head>SPECIAL PASSAGES, AND Certain Informations from ſeverall places collected for the uſe of all thoſe that deſire to bee truly informed.</head>
            <head type="sub">From the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of September, to the 20th.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Northampton, <date>Septem. 13.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Aptain <hi>Dragner</hi> having gathered neere 300. Horſemen in the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Villages, by verrue of a warrant given him by His Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, marched round the County, ſearching and diſarming all Papiſts, and all others that were knowne to be promoters of his war, and enemies to the proceedings of Parliament, from whom he tooke great ſtore of Armes and Ammunition plate, and money, packt up in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places, to be carried to <hi>Nottingham,</hi> but now tis laid up in <hi>Northampton,</hi> till hee ſhall have order from the Parliament how to diſpoſe of it</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:156089:2"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Hartford, <date>Septem. 14.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Earle of <hi>Bedfords</hi> Troop under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Captain ANSELL, marcht out of <hi>Hartford</hi> towards <hi>Puckeridge</hi> to ſearch a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts-houſe, which was ſuſpected to have great ſtore of Armes, but by the way they met with Sir <hi>John Watſon</hi> accompanied with neere 200. Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers, which were his tenants, and inhabitants neer <hi>Hartford,</hi> men of looſe carriage and decayed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, which had joyned with the ſaid Sir <hi>John Watſon,</hi> to aid him and the reſt of the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usrs, in the ſetling of the Commiſſion of <hi>Array</hi> at <hi>Hatford;</hi> but being diſcovered by the Earl of <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords</hi> Trpop, Captain <hi>Anſell</hi> ſent a meſſage back to <hi>Hartford</hi> to raiſe the trained bands, giving them notice what he ſuſpected, withall hee retreated unſeene back to <hi>Hartford,</hi> to the end that he might joyne with the trained bands, for the ſuppreſſing of the ſaid intended diſturbance: by that time the trained bands were in Arms, and ready to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them. Sir <hi>John Watſon</hi> and his men appeared in ſight comming off the hill from <hi>Ware,</hi> the ſight of the trained bands ſtartled him, inſomuch that he made a ſtand, and drew his men up to a full bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ralling of his men in warlike equipage.</p>
               <p>In this order he marcht up to the Towne, till he came within Piſtoll ſhot of the Town, his men being led by one which he had made Lieutenant of his Company, hee himſelfe bringing up the Reare, and a ſumpter horſe following him, lead by one of his ſervants.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:156089:3"/>
               <p> All this while Cap. <hi>Anſell</hi> with his troop ſtood ſtill in a cloſe way which comes from Hodſden, to Hartford, and joyns with the way from Ware, within a bow ſhot of <hi>Hartford:</hi> Sir <hi>John Watſon</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſt him, he with his Troop rode up to him as faſt as he could gallop, ſeiſing Sir <hi>John Watſon</hi> and his ſumpter horſe, before ever his Company could make any reſiſtance, ſome piſtols were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, but little hurt done, for as ſoone as the Cavaliers ſaw Sir <hi>John Watſon</hi> taken, they clapt ſqurs to their horſes and rode away as faſt as they could. Sir <hi>John Watſon</hi> was carried into <hi>Hartford,</hi> and a guard kept about his Chamber, at the bell, till they ſhall receive directions how to beſtow him, his ſumptuer horſe was laden with plate and money to the value of 4000. pounds, which was likewiſe detained. Since the ſurprizall of Sir <hi>John Watſon</hi> the country has been very quiet, he being the main diſturber of all thoſe parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Cheſhiere.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Deputy Lieutenants in <hi>Cheſhiere</hi> having gathered forces together, and marcht up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Welſhmen who were bilited in that Countie, but as foone as they heard that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments forces were comming, they tooke their heeles and ran for it, the Countie ſtands generally for the King and Parliament.</p>
               <p>It was reported that the King intended to come to <hi>Weſtcheſter,</hi> to ſettle the commiſſion of <hi>Array,</hi> others ſaid, that they thought if he came thither, it was becauſe he meant to get ſhipping and go for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156089:3"/>
                  <hi>Ireland,</hi> but theſe are but falſe rumours, for he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not to ſtir from <hi>Nottingham.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Warwick.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr <hi>Edward Peto</hi> this day ſent out a party from the Caſtle, to Maſter <hi>Dormers</hi> a great Papiſt, inhabiting at Grove-parke; where he took tenne Cavaliers with a Jeſuite, and great ſtore of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Armour, which was hid in a vault which they had made in a Dove-houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Darbiſhire, <date>Septem. 15.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>AT the Grange neere Weſt Hallam, within 6. miles of Darbie, the houſe of Mr. <hi>Poudrel</hi> a great Papiſt, was made the magazine for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts of that Countie, it being both neer Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, and guarded by the Cavaliers, <hi>Endimion Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> making it his chiefe randevouz, but the Major of Darby and the Lieutenant of the ſhire having intelligence ſecretly raiſed a troope of Dragoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and two other troops of Shire horſe, and by night marched to the Grange, where before ever they were diſcovered; they beſet the houſe, broke ope the doores and entered, where they found <hi>Endimion Porter</hi> and his ſonne, Mr. <hi>Willobie,</hi> brother to Sir <hi>Francis Willobie.</hi> Having made a privie ſearch they found a Vault which they had made to goe from the Grange to a great houſe they had at Weſt-Hallum, being neere a bow-ſhot diſtance, where they uſe it ſeemes to beſtow their Prieſts when any ſearch is made, for there they found one <hi>Atkins</hi> a knowne Jeſuite, who was in the habit of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156089:4"/>a ſervingman; theſe they carried to Darbie, and are to be ſent up to London, to be diſpoſed of by the Parliament: ſome Arms there was found, but it was moſt of it carried to Nottingham before their arrivall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Briſtow.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>ONe <hi>Maſon</hi> a ſinging-man of the Colledge, was carried before the Major for ſpeaking divers ſcandalous words againſt the Parliament, which being proved againſt him, he was turned out of his place and kept in priſon till the ſeſſions, that the Law may determine what puniſhment he ſhall have, There are many malignant ſpirits here, but they are kept under by the well affected party, ſo that they dare not be ſeene to ſtir, for upon the leaſt knowledge of either word or act the Major impriſons them, our Newgate is as full of Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers as yours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Bath.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>WE are here in a very good poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, only we had ſome Cavaliers come hither under pretence of comming as uſually Gentlemen doe at the ſpring and fall, to bath; themſelves in our ſprings, but during their abode they privately endeavoured to raiſe forces, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing them great rewards that would be aſſiſtant; but being diſcovered they ſecretly left the Town, otherwiſe wee had taken order with them and hindered their proceedings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:156089:4"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Wells.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>OUr Biſhop is turned Cavalier, for hee is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly gone from Wells, and gone to the King, the Towne hath ceiſed upon his Pallace, and fortified it with Ordnance which they bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed at Briſtol, ſo that now they are well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to entertain the Cavaliers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Yorke-ſhiere, <date>Septem. 16.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Earl of <hi>Cumberland</hi> ſummoned the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of that Countie to meet him at <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alerton,</hi> and according to his appointment, they met him to the number of 5000. or thereabouts, but when the E. of <hi>Cumberland</hi> had declared the extent of his commiſſion, they went away faſter then they came, for within 3, hours the E. had not above 50. followers, for which cauſe he was much diſcontented, and immediately ſent Letters to his majeſty of his proceedings, withall deſiring him to employ him in ſome other ſervice, for in that he was like to do him little good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Northumberland.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>AT <hi>Morpoth</hi> in <hi>Northumberland</hi> there was a great combuſtion made by ſome il-affected perſons of the Town, inſomuch that the trained-bands were inforced to riſe and ſuppreſſe them, who after they had tooke them, clapt them in the Caſtle feeding them with bread and water, And in a ſhort time, they will hardly be ſo luſty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:156089:5"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>Boſton.</dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Cavaliers by his Majeſties appointment made an attempt againſt <hi>Boſton,</hi> but Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> having intelligence ſent them word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand, ſo that they were well provided to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain them, though they came by night, many ſhots was made from the Towne, which kept the Cavaliers from comming too neere the Town, ſo that finding they were not like to gaine their ends, they retreated, but before they could get cleare, the Country roſe upon them, and ſlew 14. hurt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, tooke 3. priſoners, which are comming up to London, to beare the reſt of their fellow Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers company.</p>
               <p>On Thurſday the King removed from <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to <hi>Darby,</hi> and tis thought he meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move into <hi>Wales</hi> very ſuddenly.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
